ADRIAAN LEMMENS

NLP Researcher

Leuven, Belgium

adriaan.jm.lemmens AT gmail DOT com

+32 472 69 03 80

<u>lemontheme</u> adriaan-lemmens

@adrnlem

ABOUT ME

I've been solving problems with Natural Language Processing for over 5 years, drawing on a solid foundation in both machine learning and linguistics. I'm always learning new things, not just about NLP, and I get a real kick out of sharing what I've learned with others. If you're looking for someone who is scientifically minded, values good engineering, and can engage a (non-)technical audience – that might just be me!



SPECIALIZATIONS

SOFT SKILLS

RECENT SKILLS

Deep Learning NLP & Search **Efficient Python** Teaching & public speaking **Empathy** Attention to detail

Web dev & IS LLM prefix tuning Neural graph mining

EXPERIENCE

Oct 2021 **Doctoral Researcher** KU Leuven

- Probing LMs for latent linguistic representations that can be applied to linguistic research.
- Building an end-to-end text analytics web app for researchers in the humanities.
- Jan 2021 -Jul 2021

NLP / Search Engineer

<u>Henchman</u>

Took ownership of Henchman's search and NLP backend, successfully delivering new features under fast-changing requirements. Mentored a junior colleague and became an Elasticsearch wizard.

Aug 2019 -Jan 2021

NLP / ML Engineer

Brainjar

Consulted on predominantly NLP-focused projects to deliver end-to-end applications powered by machine learning. Example assignments:

- Productized Document AI
- Predicting airport capacity issues
- Search consultant

Aug 2017 -Aug 2019

Computational Linguist / NLP Engineer

NLP Town

Developed models, algorithms, and services for clients in various sectors. Example assignments:

1

- Automatic post-editing for machine translation
- Information extraction on healthcare documents
- Knowledge mining on user-submitted text

EDUCATION

2016 – 2017	MSc. Artificial Intelligence	KU Leuven, BE
	Speech & Language Technology. Four-month internship at NLP Town.	
2015 – 2016	MA Formal & Computational Linguistics	KU Leuven, BE
	Thesis: A simple pictograph-to-text translation system for cognitively disabled users. Prese conference.	nted at CLIN27
2011 – 2015	BA Languages & Literature	KU Leuven, BE
	Specialization: Linguistics	
2006 – 2010	IGCSEs & International Baccalaureate	NAIS, Pudong, CN

CERTIFICATES

2019 **Certified Associate in Python Programming**

Python Institute

TECH SKILLS

Natural Language Processing (NLP)	Software Engineering	
Wide range of applications \cdot Neural transfer \cdot Linguistic intuition \cdot Fast data generation & annotation \cdot Intimate knowledge of OSS libraries \cdot Historical knowledge	Backend architectures \cdot Testing, profiling, complexity analysis \cdot OOP \cdot ML abstractions \cdot CI/CD	
Machine Learning (ML)	DBs	
Deep and shallow \cdot Custom architectures \cdot Mathematical intuition \cdot Data tricks \cdot Model serving \cdot Pytorch	SQLite · PostgreSQL · Elasticsearch	
Programming languages	Misc	
Expert Python · JS · Go, C++ & many more.	$Git \cdot CI/CD \cdot Linux \cdot K8s, Docker \cdot GCP, AWS$	

OPEN SOURCE

2023	django_components Reusable Django components	EmilStenstrom
2021	sopredictable [WIP] Take the excitement out of model persistence.	lemontheme
2020	BentoML Model serving made easy.	BentoML
2020	trefwurd [Archived] Lemmatization rule induction with regex generation and ML	lemontheme
2019	spaCy Industrial-strength NLP	Explosion.ai